Guide to the Wade biography of Michel B. Menard collection, 1938-1939 MS 189
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas
Wade biography of Michel B. Menard collection
1938-1939
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas https://library.rice.edu/woodson
Wade, Houston
MS 189
0.1 Linear Feet (1 folder)
This collection consists of a biography written by Houston Wade about Michel B. Menard, founder of Galveston. Included are newsclippings about Menard, other Texas personalities, and correspondence to Mr. Wade regarding the Menard family history.
Biographical Note
Michel Branamour Meynard, Indian trader, entrepreneur and founder of the Galveston City company, was born near Montreal, Quebec, on December 5, 1805. He became a fur trader, working his way south from Detroit to Missouri, trading with the Shawnee and other Indian tribes. He later traded horses and mules for manufactured goods and built and operated a sawmill. He organized the Galveston Company in 1838 and represented Galveston in the fifth Congress in 1840-41.
Scope and Contents
This collection consists of a biography written by Houston Wade about Michel B. Menard, founder of Galveston. Included are newsclippings about Menard, other Texas personalities, and correspondence to Mr. Wade regarding the Menard family history.
Access Restrictions
This material is open for research.
Conditions Governing Access
Stored onsite at the Woodson Research Center.
Acquisition Information
Fletcher Collection, gift of Mrs. Alfred C. Glassell, Jr., 1969
Index Terms
Subjects
Republic of Texas; Authors
Document Types
clippings (information artifacts); typescripts; corrrespondence
Places
Texas
- Series I: Biography of Menard, 11583
  - Biography of Menard (16 page annotated typescript), 11584 (Folder 1)
- Series II: Correspondence, 11581
  - Correspondence to and from Houston Wade regarding Menard, 1938-1939; 11582 (Folder 1)
- Series III: Newsclippings, 1938-1939, 11565
  General Note
  In addition to materials concerning Michel B. Menard, the collection includes biographic sketches of the following Texans, taken as newsclippings from various issues of the "La Grange Journal."
  - Amsler, Carl Conrad, 19 January 1939; 11579 (Folder 1)
  - Dawson, Nicholas Mosby, 27 February; 11578
  - Duff. James G., 30 June 1938; 11577
  - Goheen, Michael R., 6 October 1938; 11576
  - Gorham, William, 1 September 1938; 11575
  - Hill, James Monroe, 24 November 1938; 11574
  - Ingram, John, 23 May 1935; 11573
  - Lester, James Seaton, n.d.; 11572
  - McGown, Samuel, 8 September 1938; 11571
  - Smith, William P. (Dr.), n.d.; 11570
  - Wertzner, Christian Gotthelf, 1 October 1936; 11569
  - Winburn, McHenry, 28 July 1938; 11568